Guide to the Fraternal organizations of Brooklyn collection ARC.147
Brooklyn Historical Society
Fraternal organizations of Brooklyn collection
1843-1997
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.147
1.25 Linear Feet in one record carton and one half manuscript box.
The Fraternal organizations of Brooklyn collection includes material from chapters and lodges of ten fraternal organizations based in Brooklyn. Items in the collection include constitutions, bylaws, meeting proceedings, event programs, reports, newsletters, research journals, yearbooks, member lists, lodge rosters, and lodge directories.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Portions of this collection were gifts of the Charles A. Brockaway Estate, George T. Hammon, George R. Kerr, Henry S. Gorham, and Edwin Selvage, dates unknown. The 1910 anniversary booklet for the Zaredatha Lodge was the gift of Edward Biggio, date unknown. The 1872-1876 meeting minutes for the Order of the Eastern Star were the gift of Peter A. White, 2022 (CBH accession 2022.016). These are noted at the file level. Source and date of acquisition for remaining items in the collection are unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into series alphabetically by organization name. Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by chapter name.
Historical note
Fraternal organizations have existed in New York City as early as 1730, when the first group of Freemasons organized in Manhattan. Generally, these organizations provided social opportunities for members as well as group benefits in the case of death or disability. Organizations attracted members based on religious, ethnic, and national origin. In addition to the Masons, groups such as the Order of the Eastern Star (for female members), Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks (founded in New York City in 1866), and the Ancient Arabic Order of Nobles of the Mystic Shrine (founded in New York City in 1870 by former Masons) were also active in Brooklyn.
The Free and Accepted Masons were by far the most active fraternal organization in New York City and Brooklyn, with over 350 lodges in 1929. However, the Great Depression marked a downturn in membership for fraternal organizations, and by 1990, 186 Masonic lodges remained in the city.
Sources
Ferris, Marc. "Fraternal organizations." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, 436-437. New Haven: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Third Kings Masonic Camp Fund publications (ARC.162)
Order of the Amaranth Brooklyn Court No. 4 records (2008.023)
Independent Order of Odd Fellows Council 837 minute book (1973.310)
Independent Order of Odd Fellows Magnolia Lodge No. 166 manuscript (1973.163)
Scope and Contents
The Fraternal organizations of Brooklyn collection includes material from chapters and lodges of ten fraternal organizations based in Brooklyn, including the Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine, Benevolent Protective Order of Elks, Free and Accepted Masons, Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Knights Templar, Order of the Eastern Star, Order of the Sons of St. George, Royal Arcanum, Royal Arch Masons, and Scottish Rite Masons. There are also two lodges represented in the collection from Queens and Long Island. Items in the collection include constitutions, by-laws, meeting proceedings, event programs, reports, newsletters, research journals, yearbooks, member lists, lodge rosters, and lodge directories.
Freemasons -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Freemasonry -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Proceedings; Programs (documents); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Constitutions; Bylaws (administrative records); Directories; Rosters; Membership lists; Yearbooks; Reports; Newsletters; Journals (periodicals); Freemasons. Aranthus Lodge No. 719 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Zaredatha Lodge No. 483 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Anglo-Saxon Lodge No. 137 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine for North America. Kismet Temple (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Elks (Fraternal order). Brooklyn Lodge No. 22 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Brooklyn Lodge No. 26 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Brooklyn Council No. 4 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Order of the Eastern Star; Elks (Fraternal order); Independent Order of Odd Fellows; Royal Arch Masons; Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine for North America; Knights Templar (Masonic order); Masonic Historical Society of New York; Society of the Sons of St. George; Freemasons. Stella Lodge No. 485 (New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Oltmans Lodge No. 446 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); American Lodge of Research Free and Accepted Masons (New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Sterling Lodge No. 817 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Society of the Sons of St. George. Grand Lodge of the State of New York; Freemasons. Jamaica Lodge No. 546 F. & A.M; Freemasons. Covenant Lodge No. 758 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Marsh Lodge No. 188 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Long Island Lodge No. 382 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Altair Lodge No. 601 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Hyatt Lodge, No. 205 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Commonwealth Lodge No. 409 F. & A.M. (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Anthon Lodge No. 769 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masonic Veterans Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Royal Arcanum; Royal Arcanum. General Putnam Council No. 1446 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Masonic Guild (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Roland Encampment No. 91 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Magnolia Lodge No. 166 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Scottish Rite (Masonic order). Aurora Grata Lodge of Perfection; Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Lady Werder Rebekah Lodge No. 281 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Scottish Rite (Masonic order); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Hannover Lodge No. 359 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Order of the Eastern Star. Stella Chapter No. 29 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Royal Arch Masons. Orient Chapter No. 138; Royal Arch Masons. Brooklyn Chapter No. 148 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Steuben Lodge No. 133 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Freemasons. Grand Lodge of the State of New York; Order of the Eastern Star. Esther Chapter No. 2 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Order of the Eastern Star. Fort Greene Chapter No. 701 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Order of the Eastern Star. Miriam Chapter No. 120 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Order of the Eastern Star. Pleiades Chapter No. 205 (Flushing, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. United Sisters Rebekah Lodge No. 59 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Werder Lodge No. 594 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Knights Templar (Masonic order). Clinton Commandery No. 14 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Knights Templar (Masonic order). Damascus Commandery No. 58 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine
  - Kismet Temple, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Ceremonial programs, trustees' reports, annual meeting program.
- Series 2: Benevolent and Protective Order of Elks
  - Brooklyn Lodge No. 22, 1904, 1916, 1918, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Roster, memorial service, and flyers.
- Series 3: Free and Accepted Masons
  - Altair Lodge No. 601, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Presented to the Long Island Historical Society by the Charles A. Brockaway Estate through H.P. Nash, date unknown.
    By-laws and list of members.
  - American Lodge of Research, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
    Presented to the Long Island Historical Society by George T. Hammond, date unknown.
    "Transactions" publication.
  - Anglo-Saxon Lodge No. 137, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Presented to the Long Island Historical Society by Harry E. Stam, date unknown.
    Ninetieth anniversary book.
  - Anthon Lodge No. 769, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    By-laws.
  - Aranthus Lodge No. 719, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Event program.
  - Blue Lodge and Masters Directory, 1928-1938 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    Directory of all masonic bodies in the metropolitan district, published by Masonic Guide Co.
  - Brooklyn Council No. 4, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Brooklyn Masonic Guild, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Blue Book.
  - Brooklyn Masonic Veterans, 1894-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
    Historical Report, 1888-1894; By-laws, 1903; The Old-Timer newsletter, 1932-1946.
  - Commonwealth Lodge No. 409, 1880-1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    1880, 1891, 1904 by-laws presented to the Long Island Historical Society by Edwin Selvage; 1898 by-laws and 1899 yearbook presented by George R. Kerr, dates unknown.
    By-laws, 1880, 1891, 1898, 1904; Yearbook, 1899; Newsletter, September-December 1936.
  - Covenant Lodge No. 758, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Grand Lodge in the State of New York, 1995, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Masonic Library annual reports.
  - Hyatt Lodge No. 205, 1870, 1900, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    1900 yearbook presented by George R. Kerr; 1917 by-laws from Henry S. Gorham.
    By-laws, 1880 and 1917; yearbook, 1900.
  - Jamaica Lodge No. 546, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Long Island Lodge No. 382, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Presented to the Long Island Historical Society by Edwin Selvage, date unknown.
  - Marsh Lodge No. 188, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Presented to the Long Island Historical Society by George R. Kerr, date unknown.
  - Masonic Historical Society of New York, 1906-1910 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Masonic Monthly research journal, Vols. 1-3.
  - Oltmans Lodge No. 446, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Booklet with member list.
  - Stella Lodge No. 485, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Sterling Lodge No. 817, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Member list.
  - Zaredatha Lodge No. 483, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Gift of Edward Biggio.
    Fiftieth anniversary booklet, including photographic prints.
- Series 4: Independent Order of Odd Fellows of New York State
  - Brooklyn Lodge No. 26, 1843, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Magnolia Lodge No. 166, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Steuben Lodge No. 133, 1920-1938 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Rosters, 1920, 1933, 1935; combined roster, 1938, also includes Hannover Lodge No. 359, Lady Werder Rebekah Lodge No. 281, Roland Encampment No. 91, United Sisters Rebekah Lodge No. 59, and Werder Lodge No. 594.
- Series 5: Knights Templar
  - Clinton Commandery No. 14 and Damascus Commandery No. 58, 1887, 1895, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Event program, 1887; by-laws, 1895 and 1909.
- Series 6: Order of the Eastern Star
  - Esther Chapter No. 2, circa 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fort Greene Chapter No. 701, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    County fair program.
  - Miriam Chapter No. 120, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pleiades Chapter No. 205, circa 1901 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Star of Bethlehem Grand Chapter, 1957-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Testimonial dinner program (1957), financial reports (1958, 1983), twentieth anniversary booklet (1964), newsletters (1983, 1992).
  - Stella Chapter No. 29, 1872-1911 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    1898 by-laws presented to the Long Island Historical Society by Edwin Selvage, date unknown. 1872-1876 meeting minutes gift of Peter A. White, 2022.
    By-laws, 1898, 1911; Roster, 1905; Meeting minutes, 1872-1876.
- Series 7: Order of the Sons of St. George
  - Grand Lodge of the State of New York, 1890-1900 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Constitution, 1890; Proceedings, 1891, 1899, 1900.
- Series 8: Royal Arcanum
  - General Putnam Council No. 1446, 1902-1904 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    The Putnamite newsletter.
- Series 9: Royal Arch Masons
  - Brooklyn Chapter No. 148, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Orient Chapter No. 138, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series 10: Scottish Rite Masons
  - Aurora Grata Lodge of Perfection, 1916, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Fiftieth anniversary booklet, 1916; Reunion programs, 1916 and 1940.